<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' []>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="info" docName="draft-latour-shutdown-ipv4.txt">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc private=""?>
<?rfc topblock="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="no"?>
<front>
<title abbrev="shutdown-IPv4">Timetable for IPv4 to Deprecated and then Historical Status</title>

<author initials="J." surname="Latour" fullname="Jacques Latour">
<organization>CIRA</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<city></city>
<code></code>
<country></country>
<region></region>
</postal>
<phone></phone>
<email>jacques.latour@cira.ca</email>
<uri></uri>
</address>
</author>
<author initials="O." surname="DeLong" fullname="Owen DeLong">
<organization>DeLong Consulting</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<city></city>
<code></code>
<country></country>
<region></region>
</postal>
<phone></phone>
<email>owen@delong.com</email>
<uri></uri>
</address>
</author>
<date year="2016" month="February" day="5"/>

<area>Internet Area</area>
<workgroup>Sunsetting IPv4</workgroup>
<keyword>sunset4</keyword>


<abstract>
<t>IPv4 is unsustainable on the global internet. The increasing costs and declining performance
of IPv4 based systems due to address overload are an unsustainable burden that is not only
costly in terms of operational money, but also in placing artificial constraints on further
development and by reducing the quality of the user experience.
</t>
<t>IPv4 will die a natural death, but waiting for it to do so will take many more years than
is currently desirable. Therefore, this I-D proposes to set a flag date to declare IPv4
no longer be supported as a globally routed protocol on the internet. The authors recognize
that pockets of IPv4 for various specialized applications will endure for years and possibly
even decades to come. However, at the time of writing, IPv4 is the current “lingua franca” of
the internet. We propose to declare a date certain by which IPv6 will become the “lingua
franca”.
</t>
</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
<t>Why is this needed ?
</t>
<t>IPv4 is over 30 years old!
</t>
<t>Dual-stack is the way to go for a while, but eventually the depletion of IPv4 addresses will
cause IPv6 only infrastructure and services to segment the Internet, those on IPv6 only
and those IPv4 only.  If the majority of the growth on the Internet will be IPv6, we'll be left
with small and isolated IPv4 networks.  It's time to look at those networks now and see what can
be done today to ensure they are part of the IPv6 infrastructure. Certainly the commercial entities
will not support expensive IPv4 support too long if there are only a few isolated IPv4 only subnets.
</t>
<t>Dual stack is an interim solution to a real problem, dual-stack has a cost, it's expensive to operate
and doubles the security exposure.  Dual-stack is temporary.
</t>
<t>The dates specified are suggestion only and need to be agreed on, they are to provoke a reaction,
to think about the impacts of shutting down IPv4, to think of the global actions we need to take
in order to have an IPv6 only Internet.
</t>
<t>There are many reasons to do this, but the most obvious one is that progress on any task
without a specific deadline tends to proceed at a slower pace than one with a deadline.
In this case, the lack of a deadline has lead o a 20+ year procrastination in deployment
of IPv6. We have been suffering the consequences of IPv4 address shortage since the first
deployment of NAT for address conservation. This has gone on for so long that there are
those who have moved beyond acceptance of these limitations to a form of Stockholm
syndrom-like support for NAT. Even with the various address sharing technologies and
their attendant tradeoffs, IPv4 is strained and we are seeing increasing costs in operations,
in address acquisition, and in various other aspects of maintaining an IPv4 network.
In short, with IPv4, we are continually paying more to continually receive a less
beneficial network.
</t>
<t>By setting a date certain for the deprecation and eventual historical status of IPv4,
the IETF can send a clear signal to developers, operators, administrators, and even
the financial markets that this change is vital and necessary to the sustainable operation
of the internet and that plans are in place for achieving this goal.
</t>
<t>In terms if timelines, we propose to deprecate IPv4 in 2022/02/01 and move the status to
historical on 2024/04/04.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="notational-conventions" title="Notational Conventions">

<section anchor="rfc2119-keywords" title="RFC2119 Keywords">
<t>The key words &quot;MUST&quot;, &quot;MUST NOT&quot;, &quot;REQUIRED&quot;, &quot;SHALL&quot;,
&quot;SHALL NOT&quot;, &quot;SHOULD&quot;, &quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;, &quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;MAY&quot;, and
&quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this document are to be interpreted as described
in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="what-is-the-goal-" title="What is the goal ?">
<t>The primary goal of this I-D is to define key dates and document a timeline and action
plan that for the discontinuation of the IPv4 protocol on the global Internet.  The dates
need to be aggressive enough to avoid further deployment procrastination.
</t>
<t>The dates need to allow sufficient time to identity potential IPv4 only networks (those who can't
afford to upgrade their IPv4 only network equipment) and plan for upgrades.
</t>

<section anchor="when-" title="When ?">
<t>The target date to have an IPv6 only Internet is April 4, 2024.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="can-i-still-use-ipv4-in-my-internal-networks" title="Can I still use IPv4 in my Internal networks?">
<t>Yes, IPv4 can exist inside Internal networks, IPv4 can be tunneled over IPv6 on the global Internet.
This I-D only addresses IPv4 on the global Internet.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="multiphase-ipv4-deprecation" title="Multiphase IPv4 deprecation">
<t>A phased approach is recommended over a few years to gradually remove the dependence on IPv4.
<vspace/>
We should start deprecating IPv4 names and finish with removing all global Internet IPv4 routes.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="remove-ipv4-from-tld-registries-and-root-zone" title="Remove IPv4 from TLD Registries and Root zone">
<t>Remove IPv4 NS records
Remove IPv4 glue records
Remove IPv4 registry access, EPP access
</t>

<section anchor="execution-date" title="Execution Date">
<t>This phase is schedule for 2022/02/01
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="expected-impact" title="Expected Impact">
<t>TLD Domains names are IPv6 only
The majority of Internet traffic is over IPv6
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="remove-ipv4-from-iana-registries" title="Remove IPv4 from IANA Registries">
<t>ARPA zone management, remove all IPv4 related zones;
Remove in-addr.arpa
Remove IPv4 in as112.arpa
Remove any IANA IPv4 references
</t>

<section anchor="execution-date-1" title="Execution Date">
<t>This phase is schedule for 2023/02/01
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="expected-impact-1" title="Expected Impact">
<t>Find pockets of IPv4 that are lagging on the migration
Reverse DNS is IPv6 only
The vast majority of Internet traffic is over IPv6
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="remove-ipv4-from-as-operator" title="Remove IPv4 from AS Operator">
<t>This is the last step in shutting down IPv4, remove IPv4 routes from all AS operator.
</t>

<section anchor="execution-date-2" title="Execution Date">
<t>This phase is schedule for 2024/02/01
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="expected-impact-2" title="Expected Impact">
<t>Smaller core Internet routers.
<vspace/>
Reduced operating costs.
<vspace/>
Big Party!
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="ipv4-as-historical-status" title="IPv4 as Historical Status">
<t>That's it for IPv4. List all the thing to make IPv4 Historical
</t>

<section anchor="execution-date-3" title="Execution Date">
<t>This phase is schedule for 2024/04/04
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="expected-impact-3" title="Expected Impact">
<t>Business as usual
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security considerations">
<t>This will hopefully make the Internet more scalable, secure and cost effective to operate and manage.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="iana-actions" title="IANA Actions">
<t>Lots, TBD
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="internationalization-considerations" title="Internationalization Considerations">
<t>This protocol is designed for machine to machine communications
</t>
</section>

</middle>
<back>
<references title="Informative References">
<?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
</references>

<section anchor="document-history" title="Document History">

<section anchor="version-00" title="Version 00">
<t>First rough version
</t>
</section>
</section>

</back>
</rfc>
